<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="sk">
  <info>
    <title>Survivals and New Arrivals (s. 184-225)</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Hilaire</firstname>
      <surname>Belloc</surname>
    </author>
    <publisher>
      <publishername>Sheed &amp; Ward</publishername>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
      </address>
    </publisher>
    <pubdate>1941</pubdate>
  </info>

  <chapter>
    <title>The Modern Mind</title>
    <para>The third and far the most formidable element of Main Opposition to the Faith today, is what I propose to call
      by its own self-appointed and most misleading title: „The Modern Mind.“ How misleading and false that title is, I
      will discuss in a moment, premising here, that I adopt it only because terms are necessary to discussion, and this
      is the admitted and well-known term ready to hand. Were I to invent a new one, I should hamper my argument, for it
      would be unfamiliar.
    </para>
    <para>We note that it acts in a fashion wholly negative. It is not an attack, but a resistance. It does not, like
      Anti-Clericalism, exercise an active effect opposed to religion, nor, like Nationalism, substitute a strong
      counteremotion which tends to supplant religion. It rather renders religion unintelligible. Its effect on religion
      is like that of an opiate on the power of analysis. It dulls the faculty of appreciation, and blocks the entry of
      the Faith. Hence its power.
    </para>
    <para>We further note that it is of far more effect in the Protestant than in the Catholic culture, though common to
      both. In the former it is discovered higher up in the intellectual and social scale than in the latter, and is
      very widespread. In the latter it is more restricted in area and less accepted by the educated classes.
    </para>
    <para>But everywhere it is of the same character, and everywhere so far as its influence extends, it fills with
      despair those who attempt to deal with its fearful incapacities… And even before they can deal with it at all,
      they are brought up against the absence of a language to effect their end.
    </para>
    <para>For, indeed, we are met at the outset of this, perhaps the most important section of our enquiry, by a
      difficulty which was not known in any other time than ours: that difficulty to which I have alluded, that this
      chief adverse condition we have to examine has no suitable name. There is no fixed term or definition for that
      major factor in our present difficulties, the spirit which is everywhere a main adversary of the Catholic Church,
      and peculiar to our generation. Many a name has been attempted none has been found satisfactory; and there is
      legitimate complaint against all those which have hitherto been loosely used for the thing in question.
    </para>
    <para>That mood running through the lower masses of the modern world, of wide influence, therefore, in Europe and
      America, and rapidly spreading to the traveled or westernized in the Mahommedan and pagan cultures, is baffling to
      label.
    </para>
    <para>That name which its own victims use (and which I here adopt), the „Modern Mind“ (or „Modern Thought“), is a
      misnomer, because it ignorantly begs the question of universality. It presupposes that those suffering from the
      disease are the mass of our contemporaries and those free from it a negligible exception.
    </para>
    <para>Of course, it is not so. Most modern men do not feel this spirit. No Catholic feels it - at least, no Catholic
      who cares to remain orthodox. The greater part of really cultivated men outside the Catholic Church despise it;
      and everything traditional and solid in our civilization, notably, the peasantry of agricultural countries, leaves
      it to one side.
    </para>
    <para>Nevertheless, as it is the word its own votaries use, I will here call it by that name - but in inverted
      commas. I will speak of it as the „Modern Mind,“ but emphasizing continually as I do so the falsity of the term.
    </para>
    <para>If we call it (as some do) „realism,“ we are confused by the use of that term with a precise and profound
      meaning in true philosophy (where it signifies the Reality of Ideas - as opposed to Nominalism); we are also
      confronted by the disturbing fact that, even in the conversational sense of the word, the spirit of which I speak
      is the very opposite of recognizing the real world. It is a spirit all print and tags, all soaked in ready-made
      phrases which have been swallowed whole, without the least examination, by minds incapable of criticism.
    </para>
    <para>Were we to call it „Modernism,“ we should be nearer the mark, but unfortunately that word has already been
      assigned to a definite theological school of error, whereas the spirit of which I speak is something far more
      extended, vaguer and, indeed, of more effect; for Modernism in the technical sense of the word is pretty well
      dead, but the spirit of which I speak is very much with us.
    </para>
    <para>We all know the thing. It is the spirit which tells us, on hearing any affirmation or hypothesis not within
      its own limited experience, that the affirmation or hypothesis must be false. It is the spirit especially prone to
      take for granted the falsity of an unfamiliar idea if that idea is known to have been familiar in the past. It is
      the spirit which confuses development in complexity with the growth of good and the process of time with a process
      of betterment. It is the spirit which appeals, as to a final authority, to whatever has last been said in a
      matter: „the latest authority.“ It is the spirit which has lost acquaintance with logical form and is too supine
      to reason. It is the spirit which lives on bad science and worse history at third hand. It is the spirit, not of
      the populace or of the scholars, but of the half-educated.
    </para>
    <para>What may be the causes of this philosophical disease-and it is an appalling one - which is affecting such
      large numbers in our time, I shall consider later. Here I propose first to analyze its character.
    </para>
    <para>Upon dissecting it we discover the „Modern Mind“ to contain three main ingredients and to combine them through
      the force of one principle. Its three ingredients are pride, ignorance, and intellectual sloth; their unifying
      principle is a blind acceptance of authority not based on reason.
    </para>
    <para>Pride causes those who suffer from this disease to regard whatever they think they have learned, whatever they
      have absorbed, through no matter how absurd a channel, as absolute and sufficient.
    </para>
    <para>Ignorance forbids them to know with any thoroughness what men have discovered about these things in the past,
      and how certainly.
    </para>
    <para>Intellectual sloth forbids them to examine an argument, or even to appreciate the implications of their own
      assertions.
    </para>
    <para>With most men who are thus afflicted the thing is not so much a mixture of these vices as the mere following
      of a fashion; but these vices lie at the root of the mental process in question.
    </para>
    <para>As to the principle of blindly accepting an authority not based on reason, it runs through the whole base
      affair and binds it into one: Fashion, Print, Iteration, are the commanders abjectly obeyed and trusted.
    </para>
    <para>Let us take a leading test: the attitude taken by the „Modern Mind“ towards the supernatural - the shrine, the
      inhabiting spirit, and, particularly, towards miracle.
    </para>
    <para>Witness has been borne to a certain marvel, a thing outside ordinary experience. The spirit of which I speak
      will deny, not the actual occurrence upon this or that good intellectual ground (as of insufficient evidence, or
      what not), but the very possibility of the marvel. And it will repose that denial upon something presumed with
      regard to the physical universe, which presumption it accepts as intelligently as a fetish worshipper will accept
      his African idol. It will tell you that a mumbo jumbo which it calls „Science“ has achieved in the knowledge of
      reality - or whatever lies behind the phenomena of matter - a final apprehension which in fact Physical Science
      never has achieved, and never can; because such apprehension cannot be attained by man’s measurements and
      observations of the phenomena alone. And note that this spirit is removed by depths from that old and grander, now
      disappearing thing, the true „Scientific Negation“ of a lifetime ago. That proceeded from men who abused
      knowledge, but who had knowledge and who possessed a philosophical method. This proceeds from mere assertion based
      on something hurriedly read or heard.
    </para>
    <para>Again, this spirit, this „Modern Mind,“ will refer to all transcendental belief in terms which imply the
      inferiority of the past to the present - that is, of other people’s epochs to the vain man’s own epoch. It will
      call such faith „reactionary,“ or „medieval,“ or „exploded“; it will tell you that the Creed belongs to „an
      uncritical age,“ and in saying so it will show its own ignorance of all that vast mass of intellectual work with
      which the past of Europe was filled, and of the almost equal mass of high modern work in defense of supernatural
      experience.
    </para>
    <para>The color in which the whole of the „Modern Mind“ is dyed is essentially stupidity: it will not think - and
      that is a very strange weakness for anything which calls itself a „mind“!
    </para>
    <para>If it were an active enemy, its lack of reason would be a weakness: being (alas!) not active, but a passive
      obstacle, like a bog, it is none the weaker for being thus irrational.
    </para>
    <para>I have said that its unifying principle was the acceptation of false authority: blind faith divorced from
      reason. The „Modern Mind“ takes for granted without examination a number of first principles - as, for instance,
      that there is a regular progress from worse to better in the centuries of human experience, or that parliamentary
      oligarchies are democratic, or that democracy is obviously the best form of human government, or that the object
      of human effort is money and that the word „success“ means the accumulation of wealth. Having taken these things
      for granted, without examination, it goes ahead cheerfully under the illusion that its opponents have the same
      ideas. What is more, it betrays that extraordinary ability for disbelieving the evidence of one’s own senses which
      is the mark of unintelligent fanaticism. It will gaze upon that most hideous of human prospects, the industrial
      town, and compare it favorably with a medieval city - Huddersfield with Siena. It will call a society wealthy when
      a great part of its inhabitants are half starving; it will believe any new hypothesis in physical science to be
      ascertained fact, though it has assisted at the destruction of half-a-dozen other such hypotheses within the last
      fifty years.
    </para>
    <para>I have said that this odd habit of preferring long words picked up in the newspapers to the evidence of one’s
      own senses is essentially fanatical, and indeed the hold of this mood may be seen in the singular phenomenon that
      the certitudes of the „Modern Mind“ seem to vary in inverse proportion to the direct sensible evidence available.
    </para>
    <para>For instance, its victims will be far more sure of the existence of vitamins than they are of a nasty taste in
      chemical beer. They will be far more sure of electrons than of fresh eggs; and when the electron or the vitamin
      bursts in its turn, tomorrow or the day after, and is supplanted by the What-not, they will accept the What-not
      with equal simplicity and fervor.
    </para>
    <para>Why is this mood so dangerous to the Catholic Church? That patently it is so, we see. It inhibits men from so
      much as understanding what the Faith may be, and bars the action of a true authority by the unquestioned
      acceptation of false; we can see it doing that every day before our eyes.
    </para>
    <para>But in what, we may ask, is it a peril? It is a peril because true faith is based upon reason, and whatever
      denies or avoids reason imperils Catholicism. There is nothing more inimical to the Faith than this abandonment of
      thought, this dependence upon a great number of fixed postulates which men have not examined, but have accepted
      upon mere printed affirmation, and by the brute effect of repetition.
    </para>
    <para>Well, then, the „Modern Mind“ is essentially opposed to Catholic action because it is unreasoning: but why so
      powerful? Why should this spirit, however strong to move the indignation of the wise or the impatience of the
      commonsense populace, have also such special weight with the more shallow of our time?
    </para>
    <para>I think the explanation lies in the fact that the dupes of this fashion believe it to be based upon evident
      proof which the least capable could, if he chose, test for himself.
    </para>
    <para>Here I must introduce the last consideration which may complete our understanding of the unpleasant thing: I
      mean, a consideration of its origins.
    </para>
    <para>The „Modern Mind“ is the dregs of certain much nobler forces of the past, some of which still drag on as
      Survivals, others of which are dead. It is the base product of a better ancestry.
    </para>
    <para>By one line it descends as a degraded bastard from that high Scientific Negation of a generation now passing:
      the Survival we have already examined. By another, it derives, ludicrously enough, from the clear-headed Skeptical
      Rationalists. By another from the great republicans of the eighteenth century. In its puerile metaphysic it is but
      misunderstanding the strong scientific agnostics of the past.
    </para>
    <para>The „Modern Mind“ is confirmed in its folly by the fixed idea that someone or other somewhere „proved“ its
      errors to be truths and that the proof was final and obvious.
    </para>
    <para>This attitude of the „Modern Mind“ is due to that great advance in those forms of knowledge which are based, as
      we saw in the matter of the old „Scientific Negation,“ on exact measurement; the physical sciences and the close
      examination of documents.
    </para>
    <para>Of such measurements we make today many thousands where our fathers not a hundred years ago made but a score.
      The practice has given us a novel and astonishing collection of powers over the physical universe, and not a few
      (though much more doubtful) discoveries upon the nature and origin of classical and medieval texts. At the same
      time, abused, it can without a doubt paralyze intelligence, and the „Modern Mind“ is the poor product of its abuse;
      or rather, the confused memory of an abuse committed by greater men, immensely superior to it. So the „Modern
      Mind,“ when it undertakes any aktivity - which is not often - confines itself to Physical Science.
    </para>
    <para>Anyone can measure accurately over and over again; anyone can catalogue points in a document or carry on a
      series of experiments. It needs no effort of the intelligence. So, when the results are reaped, the fallacy is
      easily entertained that because so much can be done without the use of the reason, therefore the reason may be
      despised. At the same time, the habit of proof by minute and exact measurement deadens the sense of proof by other
      methods, and, as we are unhappily aware when we look around us, it paralyzes the sense of beauty.
    </para>
    <para>In themselves the habits necessary to an expansion in physical science are admirable, for they are instruments
      in the noble search after truth, and in that discovery of reality which is the chief business of mankind. But when
      they are isolated and take a false place of their own to the exclusion of the higher powers of the soul, they may
      inflict mortal injury.
    </para>
    <para>Such injury has been inflicted in the class of which I speak. A stratum neither of the people nor of the
      humanists, but somewhere in between, has come, especially in our chaotic industrial towns, to believe that
      repeated and certain experiment producing proof of regular material sequence applies not only (as it does) to
      physical science, but to all things. They are the heirs of the high scientific despair of older days; but the
      unworthy and illiterate heirs. They make no reservations. They attempt no coordinated system. They simply believe.
    </para>
    <para>They have further come to hold, vaguely but firmly, that sundry men whose names they hear quoted are
      infallible authorities, because they are said to have „discovered“ this, that, and the other. Hence is it today
      that whether you are discussing the authenticity of a Gospel or Greek poem, the excellence of a picture, or the
      greatness of a nation, you find yourself presented by such men, at best, with statistics commonly irrelevant, or,
      at the worst, with the mere name of some man competent in his own sphere, but in the sphere under debate quite
      incompetent.
    </para>
    <para>To all this the „Modern Mind“ has added an ethic of whose origin it never heard, but which has for its author
      Comte. It is the worship of Humanity, and of Humanity mortal. That is good which makes men happier here - or looks
      as though it might; and happier, not mainly through the satisfaction of justice nor even by a search for beauty,
      but in seeking things much more tangible and perishable; mainly of the body. And this worship of ourselves in the
      place of God is heavily reinforced by Nationalism on the one hand, by the Communist cry for economic equality on
      the other.
    </para>
    <para>Much else enters into the formation of the „Modern Mind“… It is the dregs of that too simple creed launched or
      confirmed by the French philosophers of the Encyclopedia. It is the dregs of that German Monism and that German
      Pantheism which so much affected the nineteenth century. It is the dregs of fatigue in an over-complex
      civilization; and it suffers the organized propagation of myth, especially in the matter of man’s unknown origins.
    </para>
    <para>But in the main the source of this modern disease is the false application of mechanical methods, inapplicable
      to higher spheres of thought, which it couples with that ethic of Positivism, the worship of Humanity.
    </para>
    <para>Such are the sources. But the „Modern Mind“ is far from its sources and settled into something much lower than
      the dead or dying ideas from which it drew its own lack of ideas; much less than the philosophies on which it
      bases its lack of philosophy.
    </para>
    <para>Note in connection with the „Modern Mind“ its inability to state its own position.</para>
    <para>The old-fashioned Agnostic laid down definitely a dogma, and a dogma worth listening to. He said: „There may
      be Something. On the whole I think there is Something; but we cannot know what it is. The organs by which alone we
      can know anything tell us nothing about that Something, so let us, like honest men, proclaim our ignorance of that
      Something.“
    </para>
    <para>The pure skeptic had a somewhat different position, and on the whole, a better one. He said: „How do we know
      anything? We cannot even affirm our own selves; for personality it is a variable thing, a function of time and
      memory, mysteries no man can sound. Let us not pretend to know anything at all.“
    </para>
    <para>The day of such honest men is past, or they are dwindled to a little band. Those who oppose the Faith today as
      devotees of „The Modern Mind“ cannot tell us what they themselves believe. After we have made every allowance for
      the natural desire to shirk the consequences of unbelief, or not to lose income, it remains a wonder that they
      cannot tell us what they believe.
    </para>
    <para>And this applies not to them alone, but also to the better minds who stoop to flatter them. Read this: „The
      real trend of religion among the younger generation is away from dogmatic and institutional Christianity, and
      towards an individual and personal faith resting not on authority but on experience… The new Protestantism is not
      relativist in the objects of its faith; it believes that truth is absolute, and that God is unchanging. But it
      accepts the necessity of growth and change in our beliefs… We must sit very loose to tradition, and keep our minds
      open. Our anchor is what used to be called the testimony of the Holy Spirit, which assures us of the reality and
      primacy of those eternal values which Christ came to reveal. This is the true Christianity, and we need not be
      discouraged about its prospects of victory if we look for them in the fruits of the spirit, and not in
      institutional statistics or successes of organization.“
    </para>
    <para>Was ever such a mass of verbiage! There is no rhyme or reason in it. Not one definite statement of doctrine,
      save that God is unchanging-followed by the necessity of change in our beliefs: therefore, of course, a change in
      our belief that God is unchanging. Strange rigmarole!
    </para>
    <para>What are „the Eternal values that Christ came to reveal?“ No answer! What is „sitting loose to tradition?“ In
      what degree, where arid how may traditions be a guide? No answer! What is that „experience“ which, though an
      „experience,“ has no authority? No answer! What has he to say against a personal experience of the value of
      authority? No answer! What is „Christianity“? No answer! How does it carry on without institutions? No answer!
    </para>
    <para>Yet it is from the pen of Dean Inge, a man whose whole public standing is that of one criticizing religious
      doctrine from the superior plane of our modern advance in knowledge, and that pen when it deals with any other
      matter than religion is as precise as any now writing and as clear.
    </para>
    <para>I would not accuse such an intelligence as his from suffering the collapse of the „Modern Mind“ but he panders
      to it. He has an eye on the readers of his journalism.
    </para>
    <para>There stands the „Modern Mind,“ a morass.</para>
    <para>The great difficulty of the intelligent in dealing with this thing, whether they be Catholic or skeptical, is
      the lack of hold. It is like fighting smoke. It affords a commentary on the famous tag that with stupidity the
      gods themselves will wrestle in vain.
    </para>
    <para>What are you to do with a man who always argues in a circle? Who tells you that some political arrangement is
      good because it is „democratic,“ and when you ask
    </para>
    <para>(a) whether it is as a fact democratic,</para>
    <para>(b) why democracy is an evident good, answers you by saying that you are sinning against democracy and its
      holy name.
    </para>
    <para>What are you to do with a man who does not recognize his own first principles? Who tells you that he believes
      a thing on the authority of a name or a bit of print, and who, when you ask him the grounds of his confidence in
      such, answers you by giving another name and another bit of print?
    </para>
    <para>What are you to do with a man who uses the same word in different senses during the same discussion? As, for
      instance, who says he „believes in Evolution,“ meaning growth (which all men believe in), and in the same sentence
      make it mean:
    </para>
    <para>(a) The bestial origin of man’s body - which is probable enough,</para>
    <para>(b) Darwin’s theory of Mechanical Natural Selection, which is as dead as a door-nail.</para>
    <para>What are you to do with a man who puts it forth as a foundation for debate that the human reason is no guide,
      and who then proceeds to reason through hundreds of pages on that basis?
    </para>
    <para>Yet all that, and hundreds of derivatives therefrom, make up the horrible welter of the „Modern Mind.“</para>
    <para>Well, we must hope that intelligence will resume its rights, even against such; but the prospect is not
      cheerful. Meanwhile the monstrous apparition of the „Modern Mind“ has produced one good among many evils; it has
      produced a belated Brotherhood of the Intelligent. We of the Faith and the cultured Pagans have a common opponent.
      A common donkey blocking the car, and needing to be shouldered off the lane into the ditch, breeds fellow –
      feeling between the Catholic and the clear-minded skeptic. Each feels a peculiar disgust with the „Modern Mind.“ So
      we have, at last, allies.
    </para>
    <para>The „Modern Mind“ feeds. The animal is nourished or it could not live. All moods must thus receive regular
      sustenance or perish. What is the food which aliments the „Modern Mind“? It absorbs two forms of nutrition - one
      from the imposed elementary school, one from the popular press. Between them they secure the continuity and
      permanence of the „Modern Mind.“ These two instruments were unknown to the past; they are of strong effect on the
      present. They are of effect throughout the whole of the modern European and American world, and their effect is
      increasing. I will state them in their order.
    </para>
    <para>The first thing to be said about universal compulsory instruction as it is now arranged, is that it is
      necessarily at issue with the Catholic conception of society because it sets out upon a first principle which the
      Catholic conception of society denies. That is not a judgment agreeable to modern fashion, but it is true; and
      before we consider the particular way in which this institution sustains the „Modern Mind“, we must appreciate how
      and why it necessarily clashes with that Faith to which the „Modern Mind“ is now the principal obstacle.
    </para>
    <para>This first principle upon which universal compulsory instruction is based is the idea that a certain minimum
      of instruction in a certain category of learning is the first essential to right living. Other things come after;
      but a knowledge of these, at least, is indispensable to man and society, and must therefore be imposed on all by
      force. This category includes letters, that is, reading and writing, elementary arithmetic, by which ordinary
      civic occupations are carried on, some very general knowledge of the past and of contemporary nations, their
      geography and character, the whole tinctured with the (today) inevitable religion of Nationalism and a vague
      general ethic, humanitarian and therefore (unwittingly) positivist.
    </para>
    <para>These having been imposed upon every child of the community by force, whether the parents are willing or
      unwilling, its other activities, such as religion, seem subsidiary. They may or may not be engaged in, and whether
      they are engaged in or not is indifferent to society and therefore to the State.
    </para>
    <para>The Catholic conception of human nature is actively at issue with this. According to it, the first, the most
      necessary thing, is the teaching of the children, affirmatively, as a divine truth necessary not only to the
      conduct of its own life, but also to that of all society, the doctrines and the particular, defined, morals of the
      Catholic Church.
    </para>
    <para>In comparison with instruction in that one prime essential, nothing else counts. It is good to be able to read
      and write and cast up simple sums; it is better still to know something of the past of one’s people, and to have a
      true idea of the world around one. But these are nothing compared with the Faith.
    </para>
    <para>Here is the first point of conflict between the Church and her enemies in the matter of this new instrument
      which is beginning to be of such prodigious effect throughout our imperiled civilization. Next let it be noted
      that there is another issue perhaps even graver, and that is, the issue between the Family and the State and
      between the full multiple life of free will in action and the uniform restricted death-in-life of things done by
      constraint and on a mechanical model.
    </para>
    <para>As between the Family and the State, Catholic doctrine is fixed. The family is the unit. The parent is the
      natural authority (auctoritas auctoris). The State is secondary to the family, and especially in the matter of
      forming a child’s character by education. Now here the State of today flatly contradicts Catholic doctrine. It
      says to the parent, „What you will for your child must yield to what I will. If our wills are coincident, well and
      good. If not, yours must suffer. I am master.“ At least, so the State speaks to the poorer parent; to the richer
      it is more polite.
    </para>
    <para>Many Catholics are afraid to say so, but that is, in Catholic terms, abominably bad morals: the morals of
      tyranny.
    </para>
    <para>The issue between free will and constraint is less direct - but it is very real. It is not without
      significance that the claim to interfere by force not only in the all-important character of early instruction,
      but in a score of other domestic things, has gone side by side with the spread of fatalism in the world and with
      the inhuman concept of unalterable mechanical laws. It is not insignificant that the Church in the rare places and
      times when She had power to do so, did not compel the mind. During all that intense intellectual life of the
      thirteenth century, instruction was by choice: endowed - so that the poorest could reach the highest inspiration,
      but at the choice of the individual or family will, to be taken or left.
    </para>
    <para>Compulsory universal instruction, then, clashes with every canon of Catholic social ethics, even in its
      compulsion, even in its universality, but especially in its choice of what it calls essentials.
    </para>
    <para>Although these things are so, one may hear from the „Modern Mind“ a plea which it is so confused as to hold
      applicable. It advances this argument: „I do not say that the things imposed by force upon the mass of young minds
      are the most ultimately important. All I say is that they are what none will differ about and what all will agree
      to be necessary to life in society. As to other, perhaps more important, but debated things, I keep neutral.“ Yet
      it should be evident that how things are taught, even things which have no direct relation with religious
      teaching, makes all the difference to the effect of an education. The teaching as a whole must be Catholic or
      non-Catholic. You cannot make a school which shall not be the one or the other, any more than you can make a home
      which shall not be the one or the other.
    </para>
    <para>It is one of the sure tests of stupidity in those who discuss this matter when they put forward the plea that
      religion cannot i come into the teaching of arithmetic; the very same people would violently object to having
      their own children taught arithmetic by one of whose morals and outlook they disapproved.
    </para>
    <para>But arithmetic is not the only thing taught. Some kind of morals must be taught. And here a violent issue
      arises, which is an issue between diverse orders; for the order in which you teach morals makes all the
      difference.
    </para>
    <para>Are you going to teach children that the excessive consumption of liquor is the prime evil of human life? Are
      you going to teach them that consideration for others is the highest duty of man? Are you going to teach them that
      kindness to animals is among the highest of virtues?
    </para>
    <para>No one denies that drunkenness is a bad thing, or that cruelty to animals is a bad thing, or that the service
      of one’s neighbor is a good thing; but the point is, in what order are you going to teach them, what relative
      importance are you going to give them? Everything turns on that. With one set of proportions you produce one type
      of character, with another, another. In one order you have Catholic morals, in another Protestant, in another
      Pagan.
    </para>
    <para>Truth lies in proportion. It is proportion which differentiates a caress from a blow, a sneer from a smile. It
      is the sequence and the relative weight of doctrines, not the bald statement, that makes the contrast between what
      damns and what saves. Let a child experience through the working day and through most days of the year that this
      or that is emphasized in its teaching, and what is so emphasized becomes, for it, and for all its life, the
      essential.
    </para>
    <para>Apart from this consideration - which applies to all subjects - there is a multitude of subjects in which the
      effect of teaching makes for truth or falsehood according to religious atmosphere. Take a single example from
      elementary geography. It relates to Holland, a country the origin of whose religious opinions was mentioned on an
      earlier page.
    </para>
    <para>A little while ago the Dutch authorities protested against a textbook used in our English (Protestant)
      elementary schools describing Holland as a wholly Protestant country - with sundry other remarks upon the virtues
      which presumably follow from such a character. The remark that Holland is a country wholly Protestant, and that
      the whole point of Holland is its Protestantism, would seem so obvious to nine out of ten modern Englishmen that
      they must have marveled at any protest being made: yet it is, of course, a completely false statement, and the
      falsehood is highly characteristic of the way in which a religious atmosphere affects teaching.
    </para>
    <para>Holland is a country largely divided between the two religions; rather more than half its people are
      Protestant, rather less than half are Catholic. The whole point of the Dutch example to a man trained in true
      history is the way in which a State which was, in its origins, artificially created by a revolt against taxation,
      next strengthened by a violently anti-Catholic temper, maintained for generations by an exclusion of Catholics
      from power, has come now to something like a balance of the two cultures. Yet it is almost inevitable that such a
      textbook statement should be imposed upon our elementary schools, which have to accept what our official
      historians – brought up on stuff like Motley - themselves so naively believe.
    </para>
    <para>There is a case taken from elementary geography. With history, of course, the thing is patent. If you are
      teaching the official nationalist history of our day, you are teaching anti-Catholic history, and there is no way
      out of it. The whole business from A to Z is anti-Catholic propaganda.
    </para>
    <para>Now this instrument of universal compulsory education must obviously be of vast effect, but of how vast an
      effect it may be, what changes in society may be effected by the manipulation of it, people have hardly yet
      realized.
    </para>
    <para>It originated in the French Revolution, and the first man to give form to one of its constituents was Danton,
      when he said that, after bread, the first need of the populace was instruction. The seed was sown. It was-to the
      reformers of the eighteenth century a truism that all would be well with men if they had „light.“ Ignorance in
      terrestrial matters they thought the parent of all ill. Since this was so, to make elementary instruction, at
      least, in such matters, universal, seemed an unmixed good. But how could one ensure its being universal unless one
      made it compulsory?
    </para>
    <para>Such was the chain of policy: the enormous result was not intended. The sole intention was to give citizens
      what the limited views of its authors thought an obvious advantage.
    </para>
    <para>The idea was carried out in the course of the nineteenth century more or less thoroughly, according as the
      organizations of the various nations and the degree of their servility to the State made compulsion easier or
      harder to apply, and according to the degree in which opinion accepted this new doctrine that elementary
      instruction was all-important.
    </para>
    <para>In England, with a population more and more urban as time went on, and more thoroughly controlled than any
      other by a very numerous and highly organized police, the system reached perfection. For a lifetime past hardly a
      family (below a certain high level of income) has escaped the huge machine. It has stamped its mold upon the whole
      nation and changed it profoundly.
    </para>
    <para>But if this new force has been most thoroughly applied in England, it is almost as effective in other western
      countries, and is now the strongest political instrument of our time.
    </para>
    <para>It is strange how long it took people to wake up to the situation. Even now the most of men have not begun to
      speculate on its possible use for certain definite ends of propaganda. But the great religious quarrel in France,
      the change worked by the elementary school in Britain, the recurrent agitations in the United States against
      public grants for the schools of a religious minority, have begun to make the latent power of the system apparent.
    </para>
    <para>The wisest observers now clearly perceive that if compulsory elementary universal instruction be captured and
      used to a certain end, it can completely transform the character of all society. When we remember that the system
      is supported and confirmed by the ever-increasing network of public examinations, all taking the same history,
      geography and philosophy for granted, the formidable character of this new thing should be sufficiently apparent.
    </para>
    <para>Therefore, the inevitable conflict between the Catholic and the non-Catholic conceptions of human nature, life
      and destiny, cannot but make the elementary school their battlefield.
    </para>
    <para>There are those who think the problem can be solved by the compromise of tolerating the existence of Catholic
      schools, side by side with those of the common kind - schools with Catholic teachers and the right to teach
      Catholic doctrine at odd hours.
    </para>
    <para>Such a subjection has never passed current in countries of Catholic culture; but in the Prussian Reich it has
      worked easily for a long lifetime, and in Britain for as long.
    </para>
    <para>The only peril (it is claimed) lies in sundry individual anti-Catholic false statements in historical
      textbooks, or, in morals, specific assertions opposed to the Catholic Faith. Let the Catholic object to such and
      such particulars in the textbooks; if these are eliminated, all will be well.
    </para>
    <para>It is not so. These Catholic tolerated schools are supported with State money as State institutions only so
      long as they conform to State standards of instruction, and therefore to State doctrines in the thing taught. No
      solution can be reached on such lines.
    </para>
    <para>Such a compromise presupposes a common body of truth in morals, a common standard of philosophy, a common
      attitude towards the past, the external world and the nature of man. It presupposes this common attitude to be the
      one important thing, the foundation upon which the less important differences in beliefs and morals arise.
    </para>
    <para>The presupposition is false. There is no such thing as a primal neutral core of truth with various particular
      accretions around it of Catholic, Protestant, Jewish, or Mahommedan feeling. Any one philosophy strongly held
      permeates the whole body of ideas and actions, and, inevitably, if you have a single system of textbooks, of
      inspection and regulation, of examinations, and an official curriculum of teaching, all these will have one
      general philosophy running through them. The universal machine imposed upon all in the years when the character is
      formed, will imprint its own philosophy, both directly and still more by indirect influence. If you doubt this,
      look around you.
    </para>
    <para>Such a philosophy may well be that of the majority, but can never be that of all. Any philosophy not of the
      machine must suffer, and in the case of so distinctive an entity as the Catholic Church - a thing distinct from
      all the rest of the world, understanding and penetrating, yet separate from the world - the hostile character of
      such a machine should be self-evident.
    </para>
    <para>I am proposing no solution, I am making no prophecy; but I am stating an issue which none, I think, can, upon
      consideration, deny. The elementary school, mastered by the lay State, and imposing its instruction by compulsion,
      is of its nature hostile to the Faith, whether hostile intention be present or no.
    </para>
    <para>How hostile we can see by observing that it has produced and continues to nourish the „Modern Mind.“</para>
    <para>But how has it done so? How is this novel and gigantic instrument of policy accountable for this particular
      disease? To answer that question consider the affinities between the two and the way in which they will naturally
      act and react the one on the other till each is cause and effect at once.
    </para>
    <para>A universal and compulsory system of instruction has for its first and main effect uniformity. It produces to
      a pattern. It fills the millions of a nation (at the age when the mind is being fixed) with one set of ideas to
      the exclusion of others. No mere limited freedom of choice in textbooks and teachers can prevent this effect, when
      the whole system is subject to State regulation, supervision, examination and test. Indeed, it can be verified by
      experience that there is sometimes even more diversity of result in a centralized system of education than in one
      where local authorities and various religious bodies have power of selecting books and instructors. Thus in France
      it is a frequent complaint, on the part of those with a passion for national unity, that the elementary school
      does not provide it, while in England, where the system is theoretically far less rigid, no one can or does
      complain of stray differences in its results, for there are little or no differences apparent. It is not the
      particular form of the system, it is its universal character which is of this effect. On reflection we see that it
      must be so. A body of national teachers will come into being and will be informed with a corporate spirit. They
      will be trained all in much the same fashion to the same fixed „standards“ and with the same ends in view. They
      will teach under the shadow of a vast bureaucracy and to ends set them by an army of inspectors, examiners and
      departmental officials.
    </para>
    <para>You have, therefore, here one essential condition of the „Modern Mind“; its lack of diversity; its mechanical
      deadness. This, when it is achieved, reacts in turn upon the elementary school, and each, the agent and the
      object, the school and the scholar, increases the sterility of the other. Uniformity acquired by the second makes
      easier the action of the first, and both conform to a common fixedness.
    </para>
    <para>Indirectly but more strongly still this mechanical uniformity tends to exclusion of ideas. That which is not
      taught at all to a child, or is taught as something subsidiary, falls out of his consciousness or is diminished
      therein. For the most part what is not emphasized is not believed to exist. Often, from its unfamiliarity, that
      which is a stranger to education in childhood, is thought incredible by the grown man. [6]
    </para>
    <para>Were there multiple, individual diversity as there was when education was voluntary, men would be acquainted
      in early life with its presence even when they did not experience it themselves. But, where all is the same, the
      very possibility of difference ceases to be accepted. Now the ideas excluded under our system of universal
      compulsory State instruction are necessarily those the absence of which produce the „Modern Mind“ as readily as the
      absence of certain elements in food scrofula.
    </para>
    <para>Here is an example: the attitude of the „Modern Mind“ to illiteracy. The chief subjects of elementary
      instruction are reading and writing. Therefore a weakness or incapacity in these two departments becomes the test
      of inferiority. One nation may build, sing, paint, fight, better than another; but if it has a larger proportion
      unable to read, it is branded as the lesser of the two. A Spaniard of Estremadura may carve stone images as living
      as those of the thirteenth century, but if he cannot read, the „Modern Mind“ puts him far below the loafer picking
      out racing tips in his paper. In the same connection we all know how the restriction of writing to a comparatively
      small class in the past is put forward as an example of our progress. That writing was then an art, that its
      materials were expensive, that to draw up a letter in, say, the eleventh century needed as much special training
      and expense as it does today to engrave a brass tablet - all that is missed. The „Modern Mind“ notes that there was
      less writing, and is satisfied that such a lack was inexcusable.
    </para>
    <para>And here let us note in passing a practical effect of Universal Compulsory Instruction which is at first not
      logically apparent but the reason of which can be discovered; I mean its fostering of that illusion of „Progress“
      which is so intimate a part of the „Modern Mind.“ The elementary school does, in practice, make the less
      intelligent believe that they are better than their fathers and better off as well; materially in advance of them
      and morally in advance of them. It might be thought that this folly of vain glory was but an accident of our time.
      The stupid opinion of our time is all for „Progress“ as an inevitable succession from worse to better - Wednesday
      better than Tuesday, and Tuesday, than Monday. This illusion, bred of Pride and Ignorance, appears (it may be
      said) in our official instruction, because it happens to be the fashion. Let the mood change, let some succession
      of catastrophes awaken in men a sense of decline, and vulgar opinion will renounce the illusion of Progress, will
      praise the past at the expense of the present, and the new mood will reflect itself in all institutions, including
      that of the educational bureau.
    </para>
    <para>This is an error. Compulsory Universal Instruction will always make for the illusion of Progress, because it
      must justify itself by affirming improvement. It would stultify itself if it did not regard itself as a
      progressive good, and a proof of continued advance from a time in which it was unknown.
    </para>
    <para>Universal Compulsory Instruction contains also on its compulsory side, as well as in the matter of its
      universality, a force making for the creation of the „Modern Mind.“ Compulsion, long continued, breeds acceptance;
      and the acceptance without question of such authority as it meets - especially that of print – „blind faith“ we
      have said, „divorced from reason“ is a very mark of the „Modern Mind.“
    </para>
    <para>This atmosphere of compulsion pervades the whole affair. It is not the presence of compulsion affirmed in the
      laws (upon which Elementary State Instruction is based today) which counts here, it is the daily practice of it by
      millions - by all. The Parent does not choose his child’s instructor nor the nature of his teaching, both are
      imposed by the Civil Authority. The child goes daily to and from that institution, has its whole life colored by
      it, knows that its attendance is not an order of its parents but a public command enforced by the Police.
    </para>
    <para>All teaching is dogmatic. Dogma, indeed, means only „a thing taught,“ and teaching not dogmatic would cease to
      be teaching and would become discussion and doubt. But this new sort of teaching by force has an added effect,
      beyond that found in any other kind of teaching. It is at once teaching and law, and those subjected to it are
      inoculated from its earliest years with a paralysis in the faculty of distinction - of clarity in thought through
      analysis. Look around you and note the incapacity for strict argument, the impatience with exact definition, the
      aversion to controversy (mother of all truth) and the facility in mere affirmation. Herein lies their root.
    </para>
    <para>The second great new instrument nourishing the „Modern Mind“ is the popular Press. Here, happily, there is not
      such an issue as in the case of compulsory education.
    </para>
    <para>In the field of compulsory education the issue is absolute and inevitable. A universal and homogeneous system
      of compulsory instruction imposed by the State upon the family cannot fit in with the Catholic Church. Even with a
      society homogeneously Catholic it could not fit, for automatically the Catholic spirit would dissolve its
      compulsory quality and its mechanical uniformity of universal action. The Catholic spirit automatically restores
      diversity of mind and freedom.
    </para>
  </chapter>
</book>